A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Board on Overseas Training and Research, Office of the Chairman, Office Files of Gordon Gray FA517
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Board on Overseas Training and Research, Office of the Chairman, Office Files of Gordon Gray
Bulk, 1952-1954 1952-1955
1952-1954
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA517
1.2 Cubic Feet
The Board on Overseas Training and Research records span from 1952 to 1955 and comprise the office files of Mr. Gray, the first chairman of the Board on Overseas Training and Research. The Overseas Training and Research program was established in 1952 as a means of demystifying the cultures and communities overseas and improving the skills of social service professionals serving both in the United States and abroad. The program's board launched a fellowship to encourage college graduates, graduate students, and young professionals to pursue compelling research projects of cultural, educational, and historic value. The collection includes correspondence concerning the establishment of the Board on Overseas Training and Research, meeting minutes of the Board, reports regarding the development and expansion of the program and the grants offered, and statistical analyses of applicants and recipients of the foreign study fellowships. Gordon Gray, President of the University of North Carolina and former attorney, state senator, and Secretary of the Army, accepted the position of Chairman of the Board on Overseas Training and Research upon the program's inception in 1952. The collection spans from 1952 to 1955, when Mr. Gray left to become Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs.
(3 document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Organizational History
In March 1952 the Ford Foundation announced the establishment of the Overseas Training and Research program (OTR) in an effort to promote peace, education, and the value of social welfare and to improve the skills of social service professionals serving both in the United States and abroad. The OTR program was designed to strengthen cultural connections between countries and help Americans to better understand the practices and politics of other countries. Such work was crucial according to Paul Hoffman, Director of the Ford Foundation, who wrote in a letter to Gordon Gray, dated March 31, 1952, that "we must find ways to improve our training for international service. And we all felt the need for a comprehensive effort to fill in the gaps in our knowledge concerning so many peoples of the world" (Box 1, Folder 1). Soon thereafter, a board of directors was appointed to oversee the program.
The Board on Overseas Training and Research established a fellowship for college graduates, graduate students, and young professionals with compelling research projects of cultural, educational, and historic value intended to enhance an "understanding of these areas, to afford advanced training to specialists, and to enable professional men and women to study, work and live" in their country of choice (Ford Foundation press release, March 1952; Box 1, Folder 1). The initial fellowships were directed at projects in Asia, the Near East and the Middle East. During the spring of 1952, the Board actively circulated fellowship applications during the spring of 1952 to universities, corporations, government agencies, charitable foundations, and individuals. More than eighty applicants received funding for research during the first year of the program.
By 1955, the Overseas Training and Research program had been renamed the International Training and Research program and the board which oversaw the unit became an Advisory Committee. The International Training and Research program merged with several other Foundation programs in 1966 to create the International Division, a single unit comprising all international work undertaken by the Foundation. A reorganization in 1981 included the creation of the Developing Countries Program which continued the work of the former International Division. In 1989, the Developing Countries Program was subdivided, separating work done in Asia, Africa and the Middle East, and Latin America and the Caribbean into distinct program areas.
Biographical Note
Gordon Gray was born on May 30, 1909 in Baltimore, Maryland. In 1930, Mr. Gray received his bachelor's degree from the University of North Carolina and, in 1933, graduated from Yale Law School. Mr. Gray worked at a New York law firm until 1935 when he left to practice law in North Carolina. By 1937, he had become the president of the Piedmont Publishing Company, responsible for the publication of the Winston-Salem Journal and the Twin City Sentinel as well as the operations of radio station WSJS.
Interrupted only by his service in the military, Mr. Gray served as a member of the North Carolina State Senate from 1939 to 1942 and again from 1945 to 1947. During World War II he joined the Headquarters of the Twelfth Army Group abroad. Following his return to North Carolina and second stint as a senator, Mr. Gray was appointed Assistant Secretary of the Army on September 24, 1947 and served in that capacity until May 1949, when he became Under Secretary of the Army. The following month, on June 20, 1949, he was appointed Secretary of the Army. Mr. Gray resigned as Secretary in April 1950 to accept the presidency of the University of North Carolina (then referred to as the Consolidated University of North Carolina). Despite his new position, he remained in Washington, D.C. for a year to serve as a special assistant on issues of foreign economic policy to U.S. President Harry S. Truman.
In 1952, Mr. Gray accepted the position of Chairman of the Ford Foundation's newly established Board on Overseas Training and Research. He was instrumental in the early development of the Board and the program, and oversaw the creation of the OTR fellowship program, the refinement of the applicant selection rubric, and the appraisal of and search for activities and opportunities abroad.
Following his resignation as president of the University of North Carolina in 1955, Mr. Gray returned to government work as the Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs, a position he held from 1955 through 1957. He also served as director of the Office of Defense Mobilization, Special Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, and a member of the President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board. Throughout his career, Mr. Gray retained his interests in broadcast and publishing and served as Chairman of the boards of the Piedmont Publishing Company, Triangle Broadcasting Company, and Summit Communications, Inc. He died on November 26, 1982, in Washington, D.C.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series.
Scope and Content Note
The Board on Overseas Training and Research records span from 1952 to 1955 and comprise the office files of Mr. Gray, the first chairman of the Board on Overseas Training and Research. His earliest files describe the establishment of the Overseas Training and Research program, the recruitment of potential applicants for the Board's first fellowship offering in 1952, and the evaluation of research proposals.
In addition, the meeting minutes of the Board on Overseas Training and Research chart the progress of the OTR program as it expanded and gained greater recognition among institutions and individuals pursuing international studies.
Also found within the collection are reports produced by and for the Board on Overseas Training and Research about the development and expansion of the program and the grants offered, and statistical analyses of fellowship applicants and recipients of the Board on Overseas Training and Research foreign study fellowships.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Related Collections
Additional collections of Mr. Gray's papers reside in several other libraries. Summaries are provided below. Please contact the respective institutions for more information and access requirements.
Harry S. Truman Library and Museum
Records of the Agency for International Development: Records of Gordon Gray (Record Group 286), 1948-1952.
Gordon Gray Papers, 1946-1979.
Louis Round Wilson Special Collections Library at the University of North Carolina
Gordon Gray Papers (collection number 03824), 1919-1982.
Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library and Museum
Gordon Gray Papers, 1946-1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspirational goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation's expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed "peace" as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified "the danger of war" as the "the prime threat to human welfare today." Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world's peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford's approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford's global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation's focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation's work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration [mainly U.S. based], Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
- Correspondence, 1952-1955; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the correspondence files maintained by Mr. Gray pertaining to the Overseas Training and Research program and the work of its board. The files have been arranged chronologically. The files contain letters of congratulations to Mr. Gray regarding his appointment as Chairman of the Board and his involvement with the program's development. The bulk of the later files from 1953 through 1955 consist of letters to the Board about research projects and possible funding. Also included are periodic progress and status reports produced by the Board on Overseas Training and Research, as well as memoranda regarding board meetings, potential cooperation with other foundations and institutions of higher education, and possibilities for improving the value of continued funding of overseas research.
  - Chronological Files, 1952 (1 of 5), Mar-Apr 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1952 (2 of 5), Mar-Apr 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1952 (3 of 5), May 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1952 (4 of 5), Jun 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1952 (5 of 5), Jul-Dec 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1953 (1 of 4), Jan-Apr 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1953 (2 of 4), Jun 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1953 (3 of 4), Jul-Sep 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1953 (4 of 4), Oct-Dec 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1954, Jan-Mar 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1955, Apr-July 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Meeting Minutes and Materials, 1952-1955; II
  This series consists of the materials distributed at each meeting of the Board on Overseas Training and Research and the resulting minutes. The meeting materials and the minutes were located in separate folders when the collection was accessioned. This original arrangement has been preserved. The files have been arranged chronologically by meeting date. The files of meeting materials precede the files of meeting minutes. One additional folder of meeting materials contains documents distributed during the Conference on Soviet and Slavic Area Studies held on October 9-10, 1953. The Board on Overseas Training and Research organized the conference in an attempt to define existing gaps in area studies, establish additional fellowship opportunities and discuss the Ford Foundation's role in better preparing Soviet and Slavic studies scholars and public servants.
  - Board Meeting Materials, 3/18/1952, Mar 18, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 5/22/1952, May 22, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 6/18/1952, Jun 18, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 9/17/1952, Sep 17, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 11/13/1952, Nov 13, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 2/2/1953, Feb 2, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 5/5/1953, May 5, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 9/15/1953, Sep 15, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 11/18/1953, Nov 18, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Board Meeting Materials, 3/31/1954, Mar 31, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - International Training and Research Advisory Committee Meeting Materials, 4/29/1955, Apr 29, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1952, Mar-Nov 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1953, Feb-Nov 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Conference on Soviet and Slavic Area Studies Materials, 10/9-10/1953, Oct 9-10, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Reports, 1952-1954; III
  This series contains reports and evaluations of the OTR program and is arranged chronologically with two undated reports placed at the end. The reports examine opportunities for international education and service, and include recommendations for the recruitment and selection of applicants, evaluations of submitted research proposals, and suggestions for long-term maintenance of the program. There is also a 1952 progress report on the work of the Division of Overseas Activities, which includes an update on the activities of the OTR program.
  - "Report on Training for Specialized Mission Personnel" by Wallace Sayre and Clarence Thurber, April 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Division of Overseas Activities Standard Report No. 2, Feb 15, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Fellowships in Asia: Conclusions and Recommendations Regarding Recruitment, Selection, Terms of Award" by William Lockwood, March 1, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Procedures for the Selective Support of Investigation Relating to Asia and the Middle East" by Clarence E. Thurber, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations for Support of Future Overseas Training and Research Activities for Discussion at Feb 23 Trustees Meeting by Carl B. Spaeth and Cleon O. Swayzee (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Fellowship Applications and Proposals, 1952-1953, n.d.; IV
  The four files in this series pertain to fellowship applications and proposals, and contain documents detailing the procedures governing the selection of candidates. A summary of projects under consideration as well as sample blank application forms are included. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Three of the folders are undated, but their contents suggest they fall within the 1952-1955 period.
  - Overseas Training and Research Announcements, Applications and Reference Forms, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Statistics on Fellowship Applicants/Recipients, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Summary of Research Projects for Consideration by Board on Overseas Training and Research (Box 3, Folder 14)